<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin><pubdate>20141119</pubdate><title>USGS High Resolution Orthoimage, FY2014 Massachusetts; UTM 19N</title><geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Rolla, MO</pubplace><publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish></pubinfo></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This data set consists of 0.3 meter pixel resolution (approximately one foot), four band (R,G,B, NIR) orthoimages covering the FY2014 Massachusetts area of interest. This image in JPEG 2000 format was created from a 30-cm resolution GeoTiff by MassGIS using Lizardtech's GeoExpress 9 Unlimited software. MassGIS received 2014 four band (R,G,B,NIR) 7.5-cm imagery for Cape Cod and resampled the images to 30-cm resolution. MassGIS began distributing the JPEG 2000 versions of the 2014 Cape Cod imagery on March 20, 2015. Technical specifications and accuracy estimates in this metadata document refer to the original 7.5-cm GeoTiffs.  An orthoimage is remotely sensed image data in which displacement of features in the image caused by terrain relief and sensor orientation have been mathematically removed. Orthoimagery combines the image characteristics of a photograph with the geometric qualities of a map.  The design accuracy is estimated not to exceed 0.38-meters NSSDA 95% confidence (0.22-meters Root Mean Squared (RMSE) Error XY (0.15 meter RMSE X or Y).  Each orthoimage provides imagery over a 750-meter by 750-meter block on the ground. There is no image overlap between adjacent files. The naming convention is based on the U. S. National Grid (USNG), taking the coordinates of the SW corner of the orthoimage; appended to the name by way of an underscore is the cardinal direction that identifies the quarter-tile’s location within the 1500-meter by 1500-meter parent tile.  The projected coordinate systems are UTM Zone 18N and UTM Zone 19N with a NAD83 (2011) horizontal datum. Fugro produced this dataset in thirteen production blocks; A3, B1, B2, C2, D, F1, F2, F3, F4, G1, G2, H, and K. Production block A3 was processed and delivered in UTM 18N.  Production blocks B1, B2, C2, D, F1, F2, F3, F4, G1, G2, H, and K were processed and delivered in UTM 19N. Production blocks consist of the following towns - A3: West Springfield; B1: Gardner; B2: Fitchburg and Leominster; C2: Marlborough and Harvard University; D: Westford, Action, Concord, and Harvard University; F1: Seekonk; F2: Easton; F3: Dartmouth; F4: Mattapoisett; G1: Barnstable, Bourne, Brewster, Chatham, Dennis, Eastham, Harwich, Mashpee, Orleans, Sandwich, and Yarmouth; G2: Barnstable, Bourne, Chatham, Dennis, Falmouth, Harwich, Mashpee, Sandwich, and Yarmouth; H: Eastham, Orleans, Provincetown, Truro, and Wellfleet; and K: Beverly, Salem, and Lynn.  This metadata record describes the orthoimagery that was delivered in UTM 19N, unless otherwise stated.</abstract><purpose>This data depicts geographic features on the surface of the earth.  It was created to provide a basemap of regional orthoimagery that is accessible to various local, state, regional, and federal agencies.</purpose></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20140511</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>ground condition</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>irregular</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-72.052530</westbc><eastbc>-69.922732</eastbc><northbc>42.680374</northbc><southbc>41.476569</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>0.3 meter orthoimage</themekey><themekey>rectified photograph</themekey><themekey>rectified image</themekey><themekey>orthophoto</themekey><themekey>four band (R,G,B,NIR) orthophoto</themekey><themekey>orthoimage</themekey><themekey>image map</themekey></theme><place><placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, dependencies, areas of special sovereignty, and their principal administrative divisions, Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology.</placekt><placekey>US</placekey></place><place><placekt>U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the Identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 5-2): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology.</placekt><placekey>US</placekey></place><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Massachusetts</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>None.  However, users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full awareness of it's limitations.
Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated for products derived from these data.</useconst><datacred>Fugro EarthData, Inc.</datacred><native>The following software is used for validation of the imagery and surface modeling: 1) Pixel Factory 3.2, Linux; 2) Bentley - MicroStation; 3) Esri - ArcMap; 4) ERDAS Imagine; 5) TerraScan/TerraModel; 6) Fugro EarthData Proprietary software; 7) Adobe - Photoshop; 8) GPro; 9) Global Mapper; 10) LizardTech GeoExpress; and 11) Intergraph ImageStation Photogrammetric Manager and ImageStation Stereo Display.</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>Radiometry is verified by visual inspection of the digital orthophoto.  Slight systematic radiometric differences may exist between adjacent orthoimage files; these are due primarily to differences in source image capture dates and sun angles along flight lines. These differences can be observed in an image's general lightness or darkness when it is compared to adjacent orthoimage file coverages. Tonal balancing may be performed over a group of images during the mosaicking process which may serve to lighten or darken adjacent images for better color tone matching.</attraccr></attracc><logic>All GeoTIFF tagged data and image file sizes are validated using commercial GIS software to ensure proper loading before being archived.   This validation procedure ensures correct physical format and field values for tagged elements.  Seamlines and tile edges are visually inspected.  Seamline mismatches are not corrected unless the overall displacement exceeds 0.15 meter.</logic><complete>Orthoimages are visually inspected for completeness to ensure that no gaps or image misplacements exist within and between adjacent images. These images are derived by mosaicking multiple images to ensure complete coverage. Source imagery is cloud free. </complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>The orthophotos for production block B1 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.10 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block B2 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.12 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block C2 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.12 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block D were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.13 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block F1 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.15 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block F2 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.10 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block F3 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.09 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block F4 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.06 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block G1 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.12 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block G2 were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.17 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block H were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.06 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. The orthophotos for production block K were created to be fully compliant with a horizontal positional accuracy that shall not exceed 0.38 meter tested to NSSDA Standards (95% confidence); tested 0.16 meters horizontal accuracy at 95% confidence level. Fugro utilized the Federal Geographic Data Committee, 1998, Geospatial Positioning Accuracy Standard, Part 3, National Standard for Spatial Data Accuracy, FGDC-STD-007.3-1998 for their testing.</horizpar></horizpa></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Fugro EarthData, Inc.</origin><pubdate>20140511</pubdate><title>FY2014 Massachusetts 0.075 meter Raw ADS80 imagery</title><geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>600</srcscale><typesrc>on-line</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><mdattim><sngdate><caldate>20140409</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140412</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140417</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140419</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140420</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140421</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140424</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140425</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140507</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140511</caldate></sngdate></mdattim></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>wavelengths bands</srccitea><srccontr>Fugro EarthData, Inc. collected airborne digital photography and airborne GPS data to support the photogrammetric mapping of the FY2014 Massachusetts 0.075 meter GSD orthos project. The collection for the entire project area was accomplished on April 9, 12, 17, 19, 20, 21, 24, and 25, and May 7 and 11, 2014 from an altitude of 720 meters above mean terrain for production blocks A3, B1, C2, D, F1, F3, F4, G1, G2, H, and K; 730 meters above mean terrain for production block F2; and 735 meters above mean terrain for production block B2. The data was collected with the use of four aircraft; each aircraft was equipped with Leica ADS80/82 camera system, including an inertial measuring unit (IMU) and a dual frequency GPS receiver to support the generation of digital orthophotos with a 0.075 meter GSD.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Terrasurv</origin><pubdate>20140514</pubdate><title>ground survey</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>spreadsheet</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><mdattim><sngdate><caldate>20140402</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140403</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140404</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140405</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140406</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140407</caldate></sngdate><sngdate><caldate>20140505</caldate></sngdate></mdattim></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>FY2014 Massachusetts 0.075 meter Ground Survey</srccitea><srccontr>Under Fugro EarthData, Inc.’s direction, all surveying activities were performed by approved ID/IQ subcontractor Terrasurv. Terrasurv collected 123 ground control points to support the orthoimagery development and 122 check points for quality assurance/quality control validation by the USGS for the entire project area. The National Spatial Reference System (NSRS) was used to provide control for the network. The KeyNet Virtual Reference System (VRS) network, which consists of a network of Continuously Operating Reference Stations (CORS), was used to provide the ties to the NSRS. This network utilizes the CORS stations in the area to compute corrections in real time, which greatly reduces errors due to the satellite ephemerides, clocks, and the ionosphere and troposphere. Corrections are created for a nearby virtual reference station, and these corrections are transmitted over the cellular network to the remote station, resulting in short baselines. The horizontal datum was the North American Datum of 1983 (2011), and the vertical datum was the North American Vertical Datum of 1988, using the GEOID12A model to transform the GRS80 ellipsoidal heights to NAVD88 orthometric heights.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Fugro EarthData, Inc.</origin><pubdate>20140721</pubdate><title>Pixel Factory DEM</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>network drives</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20140721</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>ground condition</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>surface</srccitea><srccontr>Autocorrelated surface generated to support the development of orthophotography.  The surface is edited into a bare earth DEM for use in orthorectification.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Federal Emergency Management Agency</origin><pubdate>20110405</pubdate><title>TERRAIN, Charles, Massachusetts</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>online</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20110405</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>terrain data</srccitea><srccontr>High resolution terrain elevation and land cover elevation data.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Federal Emergency Management Agency</origin><pubdate>20110501</pubdate><title>TERRAIN, Concord, Massachusetts</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>online</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20110501</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>terrain data</srccitea><srccontr>High resolution terrain elevation and land cover elevation data.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Federal Emergency Management Agency</origin><pubdate>20110330</pubdate><title>TERRAIN, Naragansett, Massachusetts</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>online</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20110330</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>terrain data</srccitea><srccontr>High resolution terrain elevation and land cover elevation data.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Federal Emergency Management Agency</origin><pubdate>20110405</pubdate><title>TERRAIN, Quincy, Massachusetts</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>online</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20110405</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>terrain data</srccitea><srccontr>High resolution terrain elevation and land cover elevation data.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Federal Emergency Management Agency</origin><pubdate>20110715</pubdate><title>TERRAIN, Nashua, Massachusetts</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>online</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20110715</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>terrain data</srccitea><srccontr>High resolution terrain elevation and land cover elevation data.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Photo Science, Inc.</origin><pubdate>Unpublished Material</pubdate><title>State of Massachusetts (Raster DEM): LIDAR for the North East – ARRA and LiDAR for the North East Part II. (USGS Contract: G10PC00026, ARRA LIDAR Task Order Numbers) USGS Contract: G10PC00026 Task Order Number: G10PD02143 Task Order Numbers: G10PD01027 (ARRA) and G10PD02143 (non-ARRA)</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>online</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>2012</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>terrain data</srccitea><srccontr>Raster DEM files are used to show the Digital Elevation Model of the bare earth surface.</srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>Federal Emergency Management Agency</origin><pubdate>20120914</pubdate><title>TERRAIN, Merrimack HUC 8 Watershed, Massachusetts and New Hampshire</title></citeinfo></srccite><typesrc>online</typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20120914</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><srccurr>publication date</srccurr></srctime><srccitea>terrain data</srccitea><srccontr>High resolution terrain elevation and land cover elevation data.</srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>The original digital orthophotography comprises four band (R,G,B,NIR), 0.075 meter pixel resolution ground orthos covering the FY2014 Massachusetts project area.  The imagery for the entire project area was acquired on April 9, 12, 17, 19, 20, 21, 24, and 25, and May 7 and 11, 2014.  Aerotriangulation (AT) is accomplished as a component of Fugro’s exclusive Pixel Factory process.  The ground control, GPS, and IMU information is ingested and tie points between strips are identified.  The AT produces a bundle adjustment for each data block, consisting of multiple lifts.  After the completion of the AT, a set of stereo images in SOCET SET format were generated.  The edited autocorrelated surface model and existing LiDAR surface were imported, merged together and reviewed in the Pixel Factory processing system.  The surface was then used in the orthorectification of the raw ADS80-SH82 imagery.The rectification process was run using the processed DSM on each flight line.  The quicklook (reduced resolution rectification) of each flight line was exported out of Pixel Factory.  Radiometric adjustments were made to the quicklooks using Fugro proprietary tools.  The radiometrically balanced imagery was then re-imported into the Pixel Factory system and the histogram from the quicklook was applied to the full resolution imagery.  Mosaic lines were placed, joining the ADS80 imagery strips.  An initial QA/QC was performed by the technician to ensure that the mosaic lines were appropriately placed and that there was appropriate imagery coverage.  The final imagery data set is removed from the Pixel Factory environment in a process called "packaging" where the individual tiles are created.  All data processing in the Pixel Factory system is performed in UTM meters; it is during packaging that final datum and projection are defined.  The created tiles are reviewed to ensure the output was successful and ground control points are measured and verified for accuracy.  QA/QC was performed looking for anomalies, smears and other indications of problems within the digital orthophoto creation process, and interactive radiometric adjustment applied where needed.  Additional global radiometric adjustments were applied to the completed orthos in Adobe Photoshop to enhance the color as needed.  The final digital ortho products were delivered in GeoTIFF format referenced to UTM zone 19N projection and coordinate system (meters) using horizontal datum NAD83 (2011).  The GeoTIFFs were loaded into LizardTech GeoExpress creating a compressed mosaic in MrSID Gen4 format with a compression ratio of 80:1 referenced to Massachusetts State Plane (Mainland) projection and coordinate system (feet) using horizontal datum NAD83 (2011).  The MrSID mosaics were generated for each AOI covering the area defined by the UTM deliverable extents, null pixel values of white (255) are present wherever the UTM coverage does not fill to the extents of the SID mosaic.  The MrSID mosaics are the only deliverable referenced to Massachusetts State Plane (Mainland).</procdesc><procdate>20141119</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Raster</direct></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>19</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer><longcm>-69.000000</longcm><latprjo>0.000000</latprjo><feast>500000.000000</feast><fnorth>0.000000</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys><planci><plance>row and column</plance><coordrep><absres>0.075</absres><ordres>0.075</ordres></coordrep><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>North American Datum of 1983 (2011)</horizdn><ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><overview><eaover>The JPEG 2000 orthoimagery is organized in four color bands or channels which represent the red, green, blue and near infrared (R,G,B, NIR) portions of the spectrum. Each image pixel is assigned a quadruplet of numeric values, one for each color band. Numeric values range from 0 to 255.</eaover><eadetcit>U.S. Department of the Interior, U.S. Geological Survey, 1996, Standards for Digital Orthophotos: Reston, VA.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><metainfo><metd>20141204</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>Customer Services</address><address>U.S. Geological Survey</address><address>EROS Data Center</address><address>47914 252nd Street</address><city>Sioux Falls</city><state>SD</state><postal>57198-0001</postal><country>US</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>1-800-252-4547</cntvoice><cnttdd>1-605-594-6933</cnttdd><cntfax>1-605-594-6589</cntfax><cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail><hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM (Central Time)</hours><cntinst>The above is the contact information for Earth Resources Observation and Science Center in Sioux Falls, SD.</cntinst></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>